hello and welcome everyone it's December
8th 2023 and we're here in
2023 quarterly Round Table number four
at the Active inference
Institute let us do it Welcome to The
otin Institute we're a participatory
online Institute that is communicating
learning and practicing applied active
inference you can find us at links on
this slide this is a recorded and an
archived live stream so please provide
us with feedback so we can improve our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome and we'll follow video
etiquette for live
stream today in the quarterly round
table that closes 23 we'll go over first
The Institute scale then the
organizational unit scale with edu
active and Reiner and finally close with
some thoughts on 24 so before we go any
further Alex and blue do either of you
want to say hi or share anything or just
give any overall thoughts that you don't
see coming up later
on yeah I mean just that the year was
just so epic and um really like we're
still climbing we're still in the
exponential growth phase of our uh
Colony so it's um been amazing and
awesome to work with you guys and The
Institute and just watch it grow and
develop and all the new things that have
bubbled up it's been
awesome thank you blue
Alex yeah maybe some idea but from
current position we are seeing and
considering like now a scale of
ecosystem
scale and uh like more broad field more
more and more
people uh educational institutions and
uh startups actually last time
everything is developing involving and
we are in a good
place thank you all right so either of
you please just raise your hand if you
want to add anything on a slide or we'll
move on so first to some updates at the
organizational scale well it was just in
August of this year when with many
co-authors we brought together this
document on the active inference
Institute and the ecosystem and figure
one is still operative and totally in
effect we'll be talking more about that
as we go but during this year we did
Reach This Milestone or this checkpoint
of being able to even assemble the team
and the work this way so this was a big
milestone for us and also gives us
something like a map for the next
phase I'd like to thank our first cohort
of the board of directors Raph calman
John clippinger myself Dean tickles blue
Knight and Mike Smith great work as well
as to the first cohort of officers us
here and the second cohort of the
scientific Advisory Board listed here
also just a broader and grander and more
diffusive thanks to everybody who's
engaging if you're listening to it you
are so it wouldn't be the way it is
without everything being the way it is
so it's been a great year and we're
really excited for what's to
come if you're interested up until
December 15th we will be accepting
applications for the scientific Advisory
Board it's not an active inference test
it's about people who are beginner to
expert in active inference who are
looking to make a contribution to the
Institute in this scientific and
advisory capacity it would be awesome to
see an Engaged diverse and Global Group
as during
2024 we expect to bring the Sab through
on from where it was to how it will be
next and that's going to be very
exciting differentiating different
channels of participating an Sab memb is
not just somebody who is joining a
textbook group or not just somebody
who's facilitating project so what is it
that differentiates that that's what we
want to explore if you want to be part
of that work in this phase then go to
the website here and check for more
information about our nonprofit status
well last round table we updated that we
had submitted our form 1023 to the USA
IRS so our tax exempt status as a 501c3
is
pending in the last few weeks we've we
set up a bank account so we now can
actually receive Fiat Financial
donations if you're interested in just
spontaneously feeling like you'd like to
donate right now reach out otherwise
we'll be developing and releasing more
information on our philanthropic
development during the year and this is
a special call for anybody who has
experience or networks or desire or
feels like they have capacity to
contribute to a kind of fundraising
program in some way get in touch this is
the right time to do
it about Institute scale affordances we
continued with our volunteering and
internship programs volunteering and
engaging with projects is going to be
welldeveloped in 2024 we'll come back to
that later about the internship we had
overall during 2023 about 30 interns who
were active to different stents and six
that have successfully completed and a
handful that are continuing on the
internship has been truly amazing I
could say many many things about the
wonderful and unique work that people
did it's been some of the finest and
most fun
work about the broader information
environments and our footprint and phone
distribution there here's just some
numbers from different social media
platforms and different
channels any more Institute scale
updates from either of you or we'll go
on to the organizational
units okay on edu active the
organizational unit with a focus on
education we continued activity in the
ACM textbook group group we completed
cohort 4 so great work to everybody who
stuck on through and joined in
throughout all the videos are available
for all the completed cohorts cohort 5
again a very creative and inspiring and
ambitious group of participants who got
through chapters 1 through five over the
previous months they'll be heading into
part two in 2024
and in 2024 we'll release more
information on this soon it'll be really
exciting to continue the types of value
adding epistemic services that we've
templated over the previous one and a
half years in the textbook group related
to the integration with ontology and
math learning generative Ai and so on
and also brooch out
into more groups different artifacts and
also non-english languages blue
yeah I just wanted to add um that this
is also an open invitation for people
who have experience would like to learn
more would like to scaffold various
educational components related to active
inference or any of the foundational
skills like please get in touch with us
or if you have ideas of a course you
would like to see how can we make it
happen together um I I really would just
like to hear from the broader Community
with what what they want and need so
thank you blue as with active inference
two ways to resolve the differential
change your mind or change the world if
you want a translation of this into that
or a more accessible introduction to
this or that changing the mind is just
coming to terms with a fact it doesn't
exist and resolving the differential
that way or taking the action to do it
if it's within your capacities and so
hopefully we have a setting where both
those can happen
blue oh still raised on my side but
great
um this year we completed two courses we
had zero completed at the end of last
year and so that was a major component
of our year and works and just in the
previous months there was the completion
of the course led by Chris Fields
physics as information
processing it was a truly unique and
very
groundbreaking course and body of work
presented
some of the next steps here are to
curate and publish the 2023 proceedings
as an open source artifact and then
consider where we're at with future
learning cohorts and project-based work
in Quantum active inference free energy
principle and a lot of other
areas anyone want to add anything more
on the Physics
course and the second course that was
complete completed over the last few
months was constructing cultural
landscapes active inference for the
social sciences with AEL Ben ma Lena and
myself this was another fun Journey um
similar next steps in terms of
publishing the transcripts and the
proceedings and similarly considering
what people are interested in doing and
engaging with about active inference in
the social sciences setting a topic that
many people would I think love to
continue working in so don't be shy if
you want to continue that
work outside of the
courses here's the live streams that we
had since Round Table Three on September
29th
2023 we completed the physics and social
sciences courses as mentioned we had an
or stream with Anam marce one we had two
paper base live stream series with a0o
background and context and a one and A2
with authors and that was live stream 55
with Magnus kudal on the realizing
synthetic active inference agents
message passing work and live stream 56
with blue and with Alexander Aria on the
cognitive modeling and Mortal
computation both were just incredible
Rich epistemic resources and we had 10
guest streams over that time covering
topics ranging from AI Safety and
Security thermodynamic Ai and World
models neural Linguistics philosophy
symbology architecture really fun panel
of guest streams and we plan to do an
end of December review stream possibly
formatted as a comedy so whether you
think that you'd like to joke or just
laugh let us know if you're interested
in that also we introduced a new series
which was the active inference insights
podcast series that was led by Darius
parvy Wayne and with blue facilitating
this was a informal insightful and
inspirational conversational setting at
least as I saw it um the four that have
already been lined up or delivered were
number one with Carl friston two with
Mal abason insights 3 with John Veri
just premiered yesterday and next week
iness hippoo in insights 4 and many many
more to come so not not to Ros Darius
here but I think the insights are
loading as Carl is speaking
blue uh yeah this has been awesome and
um just a big shout out to to Darius
who's super motivated and I'm really
pushing hard on this uh right now this
is up on YouTube and episodes are coming
out bi-weekly as just an audio podcast
right now on Spotify Amazon music we're
hoping to load up on um Google and apple
podcasts soon so it just takes a little
time for the stamp of approval to to
come through so great and following all
audiovisual production we pass off the
work to the journal where we are with
the work of Alex Holly Dave and others
are working on the continuous deployment
and development of live stream and AV
transcription curation and
publication this is a great
infrastructural project and so it
continues to release curated transcripts
which promote the accessibility of these
streams otherwise it can feel very
ephemeral with the audio content or hard
to search through or hard to parse but
by getting things into a plain text
format we're going to be able to do
incredible things with translations
captions accessibility language models
and
more those are the main pieces from edu
active in Reiner we have a little bit
less to say we have the continuation of
the works that have been happening and
there was a blizzard of research papers
coming out all over the place including
with many Institute participants and one
of our projects in 24 on knowledge
engineering will be how to effectively
curate the research that is coming out
as well as hosting research at The
Institute so that we can have a summary
and be able to come back to you for a
future round table and just have a nice
Grid or list of what works came out
across different fields Fields across
different topics different languages and
so on okay on to the fun of where we go
in
24 so Alex and blue all all look forward
to your thoughts as we continue here so
first just speaking to the Institute
scale of where we're going in
2024 here we have the figure one from
our ecosystem paper and some version
and continuations are shown
here in 2024 we are going to have the
second cohorts of our board of directors
second cohorts of our officers these
will be all the same people continuing
on we will have the third cohort of our
scientific Advisory Board as discussed a
little bit earlier and we'll have two
1.0 that's going to be the
organizational unit lead who's the
blanket or the interface between the
Institute scale and the project
scale in the edac education unit and in
the re inference Research Unit and we're
also due to the recently mentioned
capacities be engaging in a
philanthropic and Grant application and
hopefully receipt 1.0 so these are some
of the upstairs changes at the
Institute anything blue or Alex you want
to add or just like that's exciting
or anything
here cool carrying on then to the
project scale projects are where the
work is these are where the rubbers are
hitting the
roads on the
left is an image from Chris fields's
Quantum active inference work and
briefly we have a classical
screen with two systems that are
communicating across the holographic
screen with a class classically
inscribed information so we have Quantum
Alice and Quantum Bob communicating
through this interface so aligned with
our roots in active inference system
engineering open science and cognitive
security we will be implementing a
multiscale temporal architecture for
Project Life Cycle management bringing
out pieces that we didn't have in 23 and
24 as we will hopefully for years and
years to come we'll be considering
projects as active or inactive at the
quarterly scale not unlike a class but
also not like a class but also like a
class projects will be proposed for
activity status by a facilitator who
takes that responsibility and
accountability before the quarter this
corresponds to preparation
so Quantum measurement
preparation we'll provide a form that
will ask about the structure function
and impacts of the project how does this
project contribute to the accessibility
of active inference how does this
project contribute to the rigor of
active inference how does this project
contribute to the applicability of
active inference and so on just some
questions for people to start thinking
about we will review those proposals to
determine if they're prepar to make that
measurements at The Institute projects
will convene and be carried out through
the quarter based upon what resources
they do or don't need from The Institute
maybe a synchronous meeting link maybe a
Discord Channel maybe something else and
at the end of the quarter there will be
the measurement phase prepare measure
prepare measure and in that measurement
we'll be looking to hear back from the
projects ask in something like the
shadow of what we asked them to prepare
for how did your work contribute to
accessibility and so on that will
constitute the
measurement then we will curate those
measurements for you all and present
them at the round table and discuss them
with the scientific Advisory Board where
we'll then make assessments and
reallocations we hope to continue to
scaffold the efficacy and efficiency of
faster time scales of inference
attention and learning on through slower
lifelong and intergenerational
scales this is just about the timing of
the projects so let's go into what those
project types are or will be in 24 and
then BL Alex please feel fre to make
some comments so we'll be separating
things out into broadly three categories
of projects first category of project
are going to be in Institute core
projects these are infrastructural and
open science ecosystem type services
such as the active inference ontology
translations and
applications production audiovisual
production with a live streams and
podcasts active inference Journal
reproduction transcriptions and
translations digests this will be
grappling with a volume of Publications
and different form and active inference
and also developing some Communications
channels that people can opt into at for
example different levels of technical
depth and different languages active
blocker active inference generative
modeling using cat cat knowledge
engineering supporting the digest work
educational activities qualifications
course development groups and so on
service and governance activities and
communication activities so these are
CORE Institute projects
and by separating out those projects
we'll be able to have a little bit more
clarity about this middle category which
just tentatively are considered as
Institute hosted projects so it's a
project hosted at The
Institute these projects are nested
under either edu active or Reiner
whether they are more of an
educational project or research project
and there's going to be a few different
categories or types Within here there
will be some topical and working group
projects so these are really the system
of Interest or disciplinary or subject
matter type groups such as health
robotics Linguistics spatial web meta
governance philosophy entomology and so
on so if you're super excited about
active inference and X this is that
group join it if it's there and have fun
and if it's not there again come to
terms with the fact that it's not there
or be the one who makes that preparation
here also we'll have projects like
sanjie num J's textbook in progress and
reviewing as an educational hosted
project as well as research project so
if somebody wants to have their research
project hosted at The Institute then
that's the space for that and apart from
the subject matter and system of
type projects we will open up an
orthagonal dimension of projects for
skills and practices so this might
include again depending on who prepares
for what this could include
computational modeling and
programming beginners experts mixed
levels All the Above reproducibility
This was a really fun conversation with
Andrew P where we talked about a
reproducibility working group where a
paper comes out we investigate that
paper we really analyze it understand it
run the code replicate the
figures that would help us understand
how is active inference being applied
what does it really look like to get to
that paper being written and then we've
basically de facto done a zero so at
that point we could then contact the
authors if we hadn't already have them
for conversations on live streams or
podcasts also skill and practice groups
like math beginners and math advanced
math art and
creativity and attention management
various other
skills we will be sharing information
through our newsletter channels and
maybe with a short video and so on about
how you can propose to lead a hosted
project following that we will be
providing information on how you could
join those projects that will be either
active in the core of the Institute or
hosted in The Institute in 24 and again
it's quarter by quarter so if it's not
the right quarter for you to begin in
first quarter of
2024 prepare for the second quarter if
that's not right prepare for the third
quarter but everyone can be involved in
these projects whether or not they've
proposed to lead them and hopefully this
structure with a quarterly time frame
will help make it clear who's leading a
project what's the project about what is
in or out and then there are the
ecosystem projects
everything happening in the active
inference ecosystem which goes way way
way Beyond The Institute here are all of
the things that people are doing that
aren't included in the core projects or
hosted projects and for projects in this
space whether it's your startup or your
open science initiative we can support
through hosting your participation and
engagement in learning groups or with
other resources that can be provided and
exploring Partnerships and
collaborations and so on so this
structure for the projects in 2024 has
been arising over the last several days
it's just presented as a a sketch and a
direction if you're watching this video
in realish time semi- sync time
then consider it and maybe you're
interested to lead a project or maybe
just see where this all goes blue or
Alex want to add anything on the
projects um possibly yes want to add
about but for now we have that uh basic
nested
structure and it's aligned with
inference approach systems approach and
uh using it we are ready for scaling
activities and support
them uh as
organization and this kind of uh hosting
projects for now all projects was uh in
initiated from Institute possibly next
year we'll see more projects uh which
are born in some our communities or
somewhere but finally supported and
hosted in Institute as some kind of
platform and service for
ecosystem thank you I think that those
life cycles and those life histories
will be really exciting like started in
a conversation hosted and incubated in
The Institute for these two quarters and
then out and Beyond or part of it moved
into a core infrastructural service
functionality or and any and all blue
any other thoughts on the projects it's
all so exciting like when when can we
start where do I sign where we start I
know how do I sign up how can I get
involved
um um uh just good stuff good stuff
thank you blue yeah um we're just trying
to summarize and have some concise fun
here and recap and wish everyone a very
restful end to this year and beginning
to the
next if anyone's watching live please
feel free to write any questions into
the
chat the rest of this stream I will give
a brief closing
address then we'll look at any comments
in the live chat then Alex and blue any
other comments that you want to have so
to make a brief closing presidential
address to give the takeaway first thank
you for your attention and upcoming
action let's be who and how we are can't
do it any other way wouldn't want it any
other way this is just to give a little
bit of some timeline as now we are
completing our third year of activities
in The Institute and I just wanted to
share a little bit about that timeline
not in an overly personal fashion
but in a way that hopefully provides
some information to the kind of person
who's 28 minutes and 35 seconds into
this
video 2020 was like the do zero for the
work that we're exploring here the
background and context this is when Alex
and I met I had already known blue and
in work with RJ and cogc we explored and
researched the preset what does it mean
to
preet especially in the context of
remote teams and operational art we
started act in lab as it was then known
in
2021 we formed stormed normed and
performed a lab and we saw the incipient
structuring like an imaginal dis of edio
active and re inference in their
manifestations as doedu andtools more
like subdomains of actim
and in CAC we worked on narrative
information
ecosystems in
20222 22222 222 we had the lab in a
nutshell in the sense of Hamlet like I
could be bound in a lab and count myself
a king of Infinite Space and we left
that nutshell that Acorn and the lab
transformed into an
Institute we also had some structural
morph logical organizational development
as our first scientific Advisory Board
came into existence as an informal
informal unconventional Advisory Board
and in cognitive security we worked on
structuring the information
comments 2023 our year is now coming
towards a
conclusion having become an Institute
during
2023 was something like addressing the
question now that we're in Institute
what next well we had our first board of
directors and officer cohorts that dove
into bolts business operating legal
Technical and social and we developed
out the edu active and the
Reiner aspects of our work with a
special focus on the edac active as this
earlier presentation speaks to as well
and on a more technological note we left
behind active inference gmail.com we
still have the logins don't worry about
it but we've moved things to the active
inference do Institute workpace so
that's where we now have personal emails
and so on so that's really a nice niche
and information environment to build
in there were many unities as plural and
minimum to as well as unities as plural
and minimum four this year in the
minimum 2 domain I would Place one of
our key artifacts which was The
Institute and ecosystem as this agent
Niche
enclosure and we explored that in the
third applied active inference Symposium
on enacting ecosystems of shared
intelligence that was a really
fun participatory organizing experience
and the panel and the conversations and
the presentations were just incredible
too there were other Min twos and Min
fours ranging from different topics and
how they were brought together for
example Deans classic tetrad active
inference abduction category Theory and
dissemination as identity and there were
some other mints and Min fors that
anyone who wants to speak more about
them can talk another day but I'll just
leave them posted here and in our cogc
work we pursued and yesterday published
The Atlas specification for utilizing
Dynamic knowledge bases of pattern
languages that are navigated through
questions which brings us to
2024 who what why where when how from
here at the end of 23 and into through
Beyond
24 where will you and we go from
here
so any general comments or any other
thoughts from Alex or blue and then I'll
look at any questions in the live
chat you know as we learned somewhere in
some stream or some course that the
future is just an of a memory so where
will we go from here we really already
went do you remember where you went or
where you will go from
here I can't say I do but I know what
you're
saying okay I'll ask Alex please first
and then I'll look to the live
chat yeah maybe it's what what wasn't so
highlighted uh during this uh this round
table but um very important achievements
on educational side and actually
possibly the main change from the lab
into Institute that now we have uh uh
hundreds of people which are somehow
learned uh something about active
inference in different formats and now
in
physics that's actually great and uh
that people definitely will share
information
share uh like epistemic status for
active inference for ours
and that's really great thank
you thank you
Alex thank you I agree with
this okay we'll have time for as many
questions are in the live chat as people
ask so first Andrew is the act inference
Institute pursuing grants or funding if
so how is it prioritizing where it wants
to apply monetary
resources to the first question are we
pursuing grants or funding yes for both
our first major grant that we applied
for
was submitted in September of this year
for the NSF
pose program which was about Pathways to
sustainability for open source
ecosystems we don't know how that plays
out we close the year in a Quantum
uncertainty there but yes we do plan to
continue pursuing grants of various
kinds we've also already been a
collaborator and providing letters of
support to other people in their grants
and so we can have conversations with
people who are wanting in their own
country or in their own location to
apply for a grant to them and for their
broader impacts maybe they want to
commit to organizing a project or to
hosting some other kind of activity at
The Institute to make a win-win
proposition for us all so yes about the
funding and the private philanthropy
angle we were not able to do that in
2023 we will be doing that in 2024 now
that we are set up with a bank account
and submitted our form 1023 and so on so
yes we hope to have any and all channels
for um monetary
inflows grants and private philanthropy
and then to the second question how are
we prioritizing where we want to apply
monetary
resources that's a bigger question of
course I can't give a complete answer
but all of us are super active in
diligent on the financial and all bolts
processes so I hope we'll have an
effective and efficient way to allocate
our attention and other kinds of
resources and we're gonna do it right
blue um so just uh one of the major
scaffolding
infrastructure things that we're
building in 24 flushing out in 24 is
like our financial policies procedures
investment procurement all of these
things um and so that will be made clear
as we go forward through this year um
and then also prioritizing like where do
you spend the money frequently when
you're applying for Grants like you're
apping to spend the money in a certain
way um and so like there are lots of
projects that are as we just saw on the
list that are scaffolded partly through
or hosted by The Institute and like we
are happy to um also facilitate and
scaffold the seeking of funding for
these projects um so as we go through
like we will prioritize the projects
that have funding because they have
funding and we will help people get the
funding if they want to um do that or we
will we will scaffold that that endeavor
to be funded to the best of our
ability thank you blue yes indeed if
after some successful quarters of
operation a project wants to lead a
Grant application and it goes to them
and they just need the letter of support
that's one kind of archetype another
method might be we identify a grant
opportunity at The Institute scale and
then pass that down and say which of
these projects can we include at x
amount and there will be step ways into
active inference
professionalism with and through the
Institute and with and through the
ecosystem so many paths just be on the
journey
okay Susan asks can you say more about
developing the pattern language Library
which is atlas sure I'll just speak
briefly to how it connects to active
inference Atlas is a flexible pattern
language knowledge database structure
that humans and other synthetic
intelligences can navigate with
questions it allows some really
interesting ways to work with different
kinds of information patterns
potentially all but at the very least
some for example cognitive patterns will
have active inference implications and
active inference specifications or
representations in that way the
composability of active inference models
and the composability of patterns will
be finding a new Integrity between each
other we'll have patterns about
generative models oh this is a nested
model this is a deep temporal model this
is sophisticated active inference this
is and so on and then we'll use active
inference for patterns that aren't
necessarily active inference
patterns overconfidence bias and so on
and be able to develop motifs that will
lead to some pretty new and exciting
ways to work with
information upcycle Club
rights is it possible to collaborate
with other authors on joint research
papers that arise and are related to the
aii course taught by Chris Fields yeah
great question so first just to address
it generally is it possible to
collaborate with other authors on joint
research papers yes within the limits of
plausibility and consent and all of that
great
absolutely about the physics as
information course by Chris Fields yeah
that is like absolutely what we would
love to see happen and just to give an
example of where that could go first off
anyone who wants to continue their work
in the active inference
ecosystem leveraging what they learned
in the physics information processing
course
please continue now if you'd like to
potentially host that at the Institute
then when we have the form for proposing
a
project then it can be filled out I'd
like to lead an exploratory research
working group on this and this here's
how I see some possibilities of how it
might apply and how it might help active
inference ecosystem in this way it's
going to be open science along these
ways of thinking about it and here's
what I'll need a weekly video link a
Discord Channel or whatever it happens
to be and then yes we would love to have
somebody lead the charge on
that submit that form and then create
that attractor so that people who want
to participate in that research can then
go
there that group could then decide yeah
we're gonna um summarize our notes and
publish a pre-print at the end of every
quarter so if you join along for 10
weeks of activity then you're a
co-author at the end of the quarter or
the groups can do whatever they want
they can choose to to structure things
how they want and then just report on it
in the measurements we'll talk about it
with future use and other use on the
round
table return to it with a more comedic
lens at the end of the year and
hopefully this will be like a really
productive and inclusive way to do
science and have fun in our
ecosystem if anyone else has a comment
in live chat just a few more seconds
otherwise Alex or blue what are your
closing
comments just thanks everyone for your
attention and work and continued
persistence and study of active
inference it's good it's a good field to
operate within and Beyond and the nice
scaffold to
have Alex anything in
closing as usual we're in the beginning
of infinity so let's keep walking
thank you great times thank you also
everyone for the comments in the live
chat hope to see everybody in the
Discord just join the voice chat be the
first one and scaffold it for somebody
else to join in reach out on the edges
stay tuned for where we go in
24 acting first
surf